Finding aid for the Blair School of Music John Cage Centennial Celebration Materials
Blair School of Music John Cage Centennial Celebration Materials
1936-2012
2012
Vanderbilt University Anne Potter Wilson Music Library Anne Potter Wilson Music Library Blair School of Music Vanderbilt University 2400 Blakemore Ave Nashville, TN 37212 (615)322-7695
Vanderbilt University MSS MUS-4
Holland, Michael
3 folders
The John Cage Centennial Celebration was held at the Blair School of Music at Vanderbilt University from March 29-April 1, 2012. Most materials in this collection pertain to the concert itself, performed by the Vortex Percussion Ensemble, the Merce Cunningham Dance Company, and Company Rose, including press previews and reviews, promotional materials, and videorecordings. Of additional interest are copies of motion pictures documenting the work of dancer Marian Van Tuyl and related resources that were referenced as part of this event.
This collection was donated to the Anne Potter Wilson Music Library by Blair School of Music faculty member Michael Holland in 2012.
The collection is open for research use. Materials can be accessed on-site only.
Copyright and use restrictions apply to some materials. Materials may neither be duplicated physically nor electronically nor leave the Wilson Music Library under any circumstances as per agreements with the Cunningham Trust.
This small collection consists of publicity, promotional materials, reviews, programs, recordings, and other background information regarding the John Cage Centennial Celebration held in Ingram Hall at the Blair School of Music at Vanderbilt University on April 1, 2012. The collection also includes copies of videorecordings and related documentation related to the work of dancer Marian Van Tuyl. The overall arrangement is as follows:
Folder 1A: John Cage Centennial Celebration items
Folder 1B: John Cage Centennial Celebration items--Oversize (held in Vault Oversize box)
Folder 2: Marian Van Tuyl items
Additional items relevant to this concert can be found within the Blair Performance Archive at the Wilson Music Library. These include recordings of the panel discussion on March 29, 2012, the symposium earlier in the day on April 1, 2012, and the house recording of the concert that same evening.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Cage, John; Van Tuyl, Marian, 1906 or 1907-1987; Cunningham, Merce; Avant-garde (Music); Modern dance; Blair School of Music--Archives; Blair School of Music--Performances; Filmed performances; Filmed dance; Aleatory music; Vortex (Musical group: Blair School of Music); Merce Cunningham Dance Company; Company Rose
Item List
- John Cage Centennial Celebration items (Folder 1A)
  - [Black folder]
    - DVD-R of pre-concert courtyard and lobby Musicircus celebration at Ingram Hall ( April 1, 2012 ), 1 videodisc
    - Vortex Celebrates John Cage: [Commercially recorded DVD-R of April 1, 2012 concert], 1 videodisc; Note this is not the same recording as found in the Blair Performance Archive
    - Postcard promoting the seminar on March 29, 2012, 1 postcard
    - Postcard promoting the concert on April 1, 2012, 1 postcard
    - April 1 symposium program, 1 event program
    - April 1 concert program, 1 event program
    - Merce Cunningham Dance Company Park Avenue Armory Events, December 29-31, 2011, 1 event program
    - Articles/reviews
      - Pitcher, John, "Cage and Cunningham are in the Spotlight at Blair," Nashville Arts Magazine, March 29, 2012, 1 printout from Internet
      - Johnston, Russell, "Cage Match," Nashville Scene, March 29-April 4, 2012, 38, 1 color photocopy
      - "In the Vortex with Cage and Cunningham," Blair Quarter Note, Spring 2012, 16, 1 color photocopy
      - Silverman, Jack, "Highlights from Blair School of Music’s John Cage Celebration," Nashville Scene, April 2, 2012, 1 printout from Internet
      - Pitcher, John, "Blair Pulls out All the Stops, Rubber Ducks and Sea Shells for Memorable Cage Celebration," Nashville Arts, April 2012, 1 printout from Internet
    - Letter from David Patterson to Michael Holland, April 3, 2012, 1 letter
  - Manila folder, containing back-up copies of David Patterson letter, programs, previews, and reviews
- John Cage Centennial Celebration items--Oversize (Folder 1B)
  - Concert poster (46 x 30.5 cm)
  - Articles related to the Merce Cunningham Dance Company
    - Macaulay, Alastair, "50 Years, 50 Minutes, One Creator: a Valediction," New York Times, December 31, 2011, C1, C10, 1 color photocopy
    - Guillermoprieto, Alma, "Merce Cunningham & the Impossible," New York Review, February 9, 2012, 28-29, 1 photocopy
    - Macaulay, Alastair, "Hard to Grasp, but Harder to Say Farewell," New York Times, December 25, 2011, 1, 24, 1 photocopy
  Folder 2. Marian Van Tuyl items
- Marian Van Tuyl items (Folder 2)
  - 2-DVD-R set: Compilation of motion pictures documenting the works of the modern dancer/choreographer Marian Van Tuyl, chiefly those created at the University of Chicago and Mills College during the 1930s and 1940s. Choreography/costumes by Marian Van Tuyl except where otherwise noted. (Position times indicated in parentheses.), 2 videodiscs
    - [DVD 1] (various b&w or colored, silent), 1 videodisc
      - In the Clearing #1 (Van Tuyl / Gregory Tucker, 1936, University of Chicago, B&w with brief color footage at end; missing part of middle of dance; dancers: Marian Van Tuyl, Eleanor Lauer, Alice Davis, and Ruth Ann Heisey) (0:00)
      - In the Clearing #2 (Van Tuyl / Gregory Tucker, 1947 reconstruction; Mills College, In color; ending missing; danced by Marian Van Tuyl concert group) (4:24)
      - Chaconne (Fanfare) (Van Tuyl / Henry Cowell, 1939; Mills College, In color; danced by Van Tuyl and concert group) (8:37)
      - Two Archaic Dances: Triumphant Figure and Epilogue to Victory (Van Tuyl / Esther Williamson, Jean Williams, 1936-1937; University of Chicago, In b&w; danced by Van Tuyl (soloist) and trio) (12:50; 14:48)
      - [Brief clip of Van Tuyl teaching Epilogue] (18:04)
      - Out of One Happening: Final Dance (Van Tuyl / Gregory Tucker, 1938; Mills College, In color; ending missing; danced by Van Tuyl and concert group) (18:38)
      - Fads and Fancies In the Academy: A Gentle Satire on Progressive Education (Van Tuyl / John Cage, summer 1940; Mills College, B&w and color; scenery/costumes: Chicago School of Design (New Bauhaus), directed by László Moholy-Nagy with György Kepes; danced by Van Tuyl and concert group) (22:39)
      - Cortège (Van Tuyl / Arthur Berger, 1942; Mills College, In color; danced by Van Tuyl and concert group) (38:21)
      - Entertainment Piece (Van Tuyl / Arthur Berger, 1942-1943; Mills College, In color; danced by VanTuyl, Lauer, and Heisey) (41:36)
      - In Time of Waiting: Entrance into Limbo, Transition Ritual, Immediate Destiny (Van Tuyl / Arnold Schoenberg, 1947; San Francisco, Scenery by Claire Falkenstein; danced by members of the San Francisco Dance League) (48:31)
      - Apprehension 1938 (Van Tuyl / Achron, 1937-1938; University of Chicago, In b&w; danced by University of Chicago students) (57:48)
      - Directions: Flight, Indecision, Redirection (Van Tuyl / Nikolai Lopatnikoff, 1937; University of Chicago, In b&w with brief color footage at end; danced by Van Tuyl) (1:01:45)
      - Opening Dance (Van Tuyl / Lou Harrison, 1939; Mills College Greek Theater, In b&w; danced by Van Tuyl and concert group) (1:06:22)
      - Uneasy Rapture (Van Tuyl / Lou Harrison, 1939; Mills College Greek Theater, In color; ending missing; filmed by Imogen Cunningham; danced by Van Tuyl) (1:12:03)
      - [Demonstration films using student studies from Van Tuyl’s Rhythmic resources class at Mills College, late 1950s, danced by Mills College students; in color]
        - 3 Durations in Stress of 5 in the Following Patterns: I.I.I/III../I..II/I.II./ (1:15:50)
        - Antiphonal Study in Mixed Stress (1:16:55)
        - Round in 3 Voices Using Mixed Stress (1:18:31)
        - Solo with Ground Bass: 4 Durations in Stress of 3 (1:19:22)
        - Fugato Study in 3 Voices, Subject: 4 Durations in Stress of 3 (1:20:33)
        - Suspension Patterns in Stress of 4 (1:22:00)
    - [DVD 2] (color, with sound), 1 videodisc
      - Uneasy Rapture (Van Tuyl / Lou Harrison, 1939 )
  - [DVD 3] (b&w and color, with sound), 1 videodisc
    - Fads and Fancies in the Academy ( 1940 ), (choreography: Marian Van Tuyl; original 16mm film footage; music: John Cage), a rough syncing of music with the choreography as a step in restructuring the work; musical performance by the Amadinda Percussion Group
  - Photocopies of descriptions to films, guides to dances, newspaper clippings, various concert programs 1938-1947, and other relevant pieces